Soviet Union Hare Krishna Subject Files, Inclusive Dates: 1982-2000, undated, Bulk Dates: 1986-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Hare Krishna Subject Files
Inclusive Dates: 1982-2000, undated, Bulk Dates: 1986-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
36
Keston Institute, 1969 -
20 Folders
The Soviet Union Hare Krishna Subject Files contain materials that focus on the history of the religion within the Soviet Union and the persecution and struggles in registration the group experienced in the late 20th century.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston gathered files related to Hare Krishna believers in the Soviet Union from 1986-2000. The majority of the materials regard the group’s persecution and attempts at registration in the late 1980s. Much information involves individual cases of persecution, including imprisonment, labor camps, and psychiatric hospitals.
Hare Krishna or International Society for Krishna Consciousness (ISKCON) is a semimonastic Vaishnava Hindu organization founded in 1965 in the United States by A.C. Bhaktivedanta (Swami Prabhupada) and came from the Bengali bhakti yoga tradition dating back to the 16th century. In 1971, Swami Prabhupada visited the Soviet Union and met Anatoli Fedorovich Pinyayev, a young Russian who would become the leader of the ISKON movement within the USSR. Following their meeting, Pinyayev traveled throughout the country teaching others the principles of Hare Krishna. The religion spread after the 1979 Moscow International Book Fair where Hare Krishna books were displayed. Throughout the late 1980s, the group experienced extensive persecution and struggled to achieve registration as a legitimate religion. The first registered group was the Moscow Society for Krishna Consciousness that received legal status in May 1988.
Scope and Content
The Hare Krishna Subject Files contain abstracts, newsletters from the Committee to Free Soviet Hare Krishnas, articles, booklets, newspapers, clippings, pamphlets, correspondence, handwritten documents, samizdat, reports, biographies, an issue of Back to the Godhead magazine, a manuscript, and a fax. The documents span 1986-2000, with the majority of from 1986-1989.
Important themes and people mentioned within the files include persecution, chanting, mantras, kirtans, psychiatric hospitals, registration, labor camps, KGB, Council for Religious Affairs, prisoners of conscience, torture, Anatoli Pinyayev, Bhaktivedanta (Swami Prabhupada), Olga Kiselyova (Kiseleva), Article 227, forced use of medical drugs, house searches, pressure to recant, religious literature, critical media, Moscow International Bookfair, yoga, Janmastami festival, and the lack of temple.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Hare Krishna Subject Files separated into several folders. Some documents were labeled and were filed accordingly. The remaining unlabeled documents were filed by date and placed under the general category, except in the few cases when they fit under existing subject designations.
The Hare Krishna Subject Files have been divided into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 36.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
International Society for Krishna Consciousness.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Subjects
Hare Krishnas.; Labor camps.; Prison sentences -- Russia (Federation).; Psychiatric hospital patients -- Abuse of.; Psychiatric hospitals -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Abstracts.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Publications.
- General, 1982-2000, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series focuses on the history of the Hare Krishna group within the Soviet Union, as well as their persecution and struggle to become a registered religion.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 36.
  - Hare Krishna. General (1 of 7), 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hare Krishna. General (2 of 7), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hare Krishna. General (3 of 7), 1987 January-September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hare Krishna. General (4 of 7), 1987 October-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hare Krishna. General (5 of 7), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hare Krishna. General (6 of 7), 1989, 1991-1992, 1995 June, 2000 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hare Krishna. General (7 of 7), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hare Krishna Communities, State, and Law, 1987 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hare Krishna-State Relations, 1988 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hare Krishna. Registration of Communities, 1988 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hare Krishna. State Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna. Harassment, 1986 March, June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna. Physical Assault and Murder, 1986 December, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna. Arrests and Imprisonments, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna. Legal Disabilities, Refusal to Register Communities, 1987 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna. Misuse of Psychiatry, 1987 September, October 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hare Krishna. Activities Disapproved by the State. Western Reactions, Protests, and Appeals, 1987 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hare Krishna. Activities Disapproved by the State. Public Demonstrations and Protests, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hare Krishna. Information on Individual Prisoners and Their Cases, 1985 November, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Samizdat, 1976-1987; 2
  This series contains samizdat documents that focus on the legal proceedings and sentences surrounding the persecution of various Hare Krishna adherents.
  - State Oppressive Practices against Hare Krishna, 1976, 1985 July-December 1986 January-March 1987 February (Box 1, Folder 20)